{"tossups": [{"question": "In 2014, California assemblyman Richard Bloom introduced a bill to stop performances by this company. This organization was fined by OSHA following the 2010 death of its employee, Dawn Brancheau. This company\u2019s second site was absorbed by Six Flags Ohio, and its stock plummeted in 2014 after it was criticized in the documentary<em> Blackfish</em> for poor treatment of its star, Tilikum. For the point, name this aquatic amusement park known for its Shamu shows, starring killer whales.", "answer": "<b> Sea World</b>", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {}, {}, {"question": "This leader won the Civic Crown at the Siege of Mytilene. When his soldiers failed to obey his order to retreat, he lost the Battle of Gergovia, but he eventually defeated Vercingetorix [ver-sin-get-or-ix] at the Siege of Alesia. This leader, whose elections were funded by his ally, Crassus, defeated his rival Pompey the Great. For the point, name this dictator who ended the Roman Republic before being assassinated by Brutus and Cassius on the Ides of March.", "answer": "Gaius<b> Julius Caesar</b> (prompt on Caesar)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {}, {"question": "This country\u2019s government arrested the former Mayor of Chacao, Leopoldo Lopez, for allegedly using\u201csubliminal messages\u201d to promote public violence. Due to extensive food shortages, the Democratic Action Party won the 2015 parliamentary elections in this country, defeating the incumbent PSUV founded by Hugo Chavez. For the point, name this South American country currently led by Nicolas Maduro whose capital is Caracas.", "answer": "<b> Venezuela</b>", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {}, {"question": "The Lizard Union was formed to combat lawlessness in this organization\u2019s territory, which was lost in the Second Treaty of Thorn. This group was headed by a<em> hochmeister</em> who ruled from Marienburg, and its fortunes declined after losing at Grunwald. A century and a half earlier, a prince of Novgorod, Alexander Nevsky, was able to defeat this organization at the Battle of the Ice. Poland and pagans in other countries were opposed by, for the point, what Germanic Catholic crusading order?", "answer": "<b> Teutonic Order</b> (or<b> Teutonic Knights</b>; accept<b> Order of Brothers of the German House of Saint Mary in Jerusalem</b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This man was forced to return to England after suffering a leg injury caused by exploding gunpowder. This person was the first to use the term \u201cNew England\u201d on a map to refer to the northeast. He made the order \u201cHe that will not work, shall not eat\u201d in trying to keep his colony afloat. This man claimed he was captured by the Powhatan Confederacy and would have died had not for the chief\u2019s daughter. Pocahontas legendarily saved the life of, for the point, what English explorer and leader of Jamestown?", "answer": "John<b> Smith</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "The Amun division of this man\u2019s army was nearly destroyed near the Orontes River, shortly before this man signed a peace treaty with Hattusili III. This ruler constructed a small temple for his wife Nefertari next to a large one built to celebrate a victory where this man defeated the Hittite Empire using his chariots. For the point, name this New Kingdom Egyptian pharaoh who built the temple at Abu Simbel and won the Battle of Kadesh.", "answer": "<b> Ramesses the Great</b> (or<b> Ramesses II</b>) Page 2", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "This man admitted his government\u2019s role in the Katyn Massacre. He allowed neighboring states to control their internal affairs via the \u201cSinatra Doctrine,\u201d and was the target of a 1991 coup d\u2019etat that started Boris Yeltsin\u2019s rise to prominence. This leader attempted to reform his country through increasing freedom of expression, a concept called<em> glasnost</em>, and economic reforms, or<em> perestroika</em>. For the point, name this last General Secretary of the Communist Party of the Soviet Union.", "answer": "Mikhail Sergeyevich<b> Gorbachev</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "This family overthrew Piero Sonderini\u2019s government in 1512, after they had earlier been evicted from their city by Charles VIII of France. Popes such as Clement VII and Leo X were members of this family, and Giuliano, the brother of one ruler from this family, was killed in the Pazzi Conspiracy. Michelangelo and Donatello were patronized by Cosimo and Lorenzo the Magnificent of this family. For the point, name this family, the namesake of a prominent Renaissance bank and rulers of Florence.", "answer": "<b> Medici</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "This man\u2019s brother-in-law, Abel Corbin, provided inside information to Jay Gould and Jim Fisk as they tried to corner the gold market. While dying, this President wrote his memoirs with the assistance of Mark Twain. He urged Congress to pass the Force Acts to fight the KKK. The Whiskey Ring and Credit Mobilier incidents were two of the many scandals during the administration of, for the point, what U.S. President who served as a Civil War general and was nicknamed \u201cUnconditional Surrender?\u201d", "answer": "Ulysses S.<b> Grant</b> (or Hiram Ulysses<b> Grant</b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Gustavus Doane led an Army expedition to explore this location. That expedition, launched in 1870 with former Congressman Henry Washburn, named a series of features in this location, including Tower Fall and a geothermal spring that regularly erupted. A massive supervolcano lies underneath, for the point, what national park, the oldest in the United States, which is home to Old Faithful in Wyoming?", "answer": "<b> Yellowstone</b> National Park Page 3", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "Andrei Zhdanov led a summit telling colleagues not to join this project at Szklarska Poreba, even after Ernest Bevin and Georges Bidualt [bee-doh] quickly supported it. This project was to include Soviet participation, as described in a speech given at Harvard. The February 1948 Czechoslovakian coup bolstered support for this project in the U.S., which provided over $12 billion in it. For the point, name this aid program for post-war Western Europe, named for Truman\u2019s Secretary of State.", "answer": "<b> Marshall</b> Plan (or<b> E</b>uropean<b> R</b>ecovery<b> P</b>rogram; accept synonyms for plan; do not accept or prompt on Truman Doctrine which doesn\u2019t fit the \u201cproject\u201d clues here)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "One artist from this country included the printmaker Jose Posada and Benito Juarez in his mural <em>Dream of a Sunday Afternoon in Alameda Park</em> and created a series of murals celebrating<em> Detroit Industry</em>. Another artist from this country created a double self-portrait in which two versions of herself are linked by exposed veins. The artists Diego Rivera and Frida Kahlo were born in, for the point, what North American country?", "answer": "<b> Mexico</b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {}, {"question": "A rallying cry in this war was \u201cRemember the River Raisin!\u201d During this war, Winfield Scott was injured in the bloody Battle of Lundy\u2019s Lane. Its final major battle was actually fought the month after a peace treaty had been signed in Belgium. \u201cThe Star-Spangled Banner\u201d was written during this war, which also featured the burning of Washington. For the point, name this war that pitted Great Britain and the United States against each other in the early 19th century.", "answer": "War of<b> 1812</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "A Christian organization within this movement was led by feminist Frances Willard and was called the WCTU. For supporting this movement, Rutherford B. Hayes\u2019 wife, Lucy, received a derisive nickname. This movement called for \u201cMaine laws,\u201d named because Maine was the first state to \u201cgo dry\u201d in 1851. Its greatest success was the passage of the 18th Amendment. For the point, name this political movement that opposed the consumption of alcohol.", "answer": "<b> Prohibition</b> (accept<b> temperance</b>; accept descriptions of an<b> anti-alcohol</b> movement until\u201calcohol\u201d is read) Page 4", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "The oldest-known one of these vehicles was found in the Nydam Bog. Types of these vehicles include the Karvi and Drekkar. In 1939, a buried one of these vehicles was excavated at Sutton Hoo. After the death of Louis the Pious left France weak, these vehicles were used to attack up and down the Seine. These vehicles enabled raids on places like Lindisfarne. Vinland was reached by Leif Eriksson on, for the point, what type of Viking seacraft?", "answer": "Viking<b> longship</b> (accept Viking<b> longboat</b>; prompt on general descriptions of ships until\u201cseacraft\u201d is read)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "Eurymedon the Hierophant charged this man with impiety, which caused this philosopher to flee to Chalcis. This man\u2019s Prior Analytics and Posterior Analytics formed the basis for his namesake order of logic. This man was known to the Islamic world as the \u201cFirst Teacher,\u201d and his<em> Politics</em> builds on the system of ethics that he developed in his<em> Nicomachean Ethics</em>. For the point, name this Ancient Greek philosopher, the student of Plato and tutor to Alexander the Great.", "answer": "<b> Aristotle</b>", "metadata": "Philosophy - Philosophy"}, {"question": "In a play set during this event, Pandarus mediates between the two title characters of Shakespeare\u2019s <em>Troilus and Cressida</em>. A survivor of this conflict descends to the underworld in Book 6 of a Latin epic poem, while another survivor of this war takes ten years to return to his wife, Penelope. Achilles drags the body of Hector around the seven gates of the target city of this war in Homer\u2019s<em> Iliad</em>. For the point, name this mythological war that ended when the defending city\u2019s walls were breached by a wooden horse.", "answer": "<b> Trojan</b> War", "metadata": "Mythology - Mythology"}, {}, {"question": "To improve the accuracy of these devices, Bahtinov and Carey invented two types of \u201cmasks.\u201d One of these devices that utilizes X-rays is named for Subrahmanyan Chandrasekhar, and one of these devices in Arecibo, Puerto Rico, uses radio waves. A convex objective lens and a concave eyepiece were used to construct them in the early seventeenth century, before they were improved by Isaac Newton\u2019s \u201creflecting\u201dtype. For the point, name these devices that Galileo used to view the moons of Jupiter.", "answer": "<b> telescope</b>s (accept any specific type)", "metadata": "Science - Other Science - Astronomy"}, {"question": "This man closed one speech with the call \u201cCome then, let us go forward together with our united strength.\u201d In that introductory speech, this man described \u201cour aim\u201d as \u201cvictory at all costs, victory in spite of all terror,\u201d \u201cfor without victory, there is no survival\u201d against Germany. For the point, name this British Prime Minister who noted \u201cI have nothing to offer but blood, toil, tears, and sweat\u201d in that speech to the House of Commons in 1940, during World War II.", "answer": "Sir Winston<b> Churchill</b> Page 5", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "During this event, the Brunswick Manifesto attempted to protect certain participants, who would later be captured at Varennes. The Thermidorian Reaction attempted to moderate this event, during which the National Convention issued the Declaration of the Rights of Man. The Tennis Court Oath was taken by members of the Third Estate during this event, which started after the storming of the Bastille. Robespierre\u2019s guillotine killed thousands in the Reign of Terror during, for the point, what revolution that overthrew Louis XVI?", "answer": "<b> French Revolution</b> of 1789 Page 6", "metadata": "History - European History"}], "bonuses": []}